Barbara McClintock Papers 1927-1991 Mss.Ms.Coll.79
American Philosophical Society
- Series IV. Works by others, 1927-1991; 4.5 linear feet
  - Transposition of Elements of the 412, Copia, and 297 Dispersed Repeated Gene Families in Drosophila melanogaster, 1979; Potter, S. Steven, William J. Brorein, Jr., and Gerald M. Rubin (Box 28)
  - Propagation of Zea Mays L. by Shoot Tip Culture: A Feasibility Study, 1980; Raman, K., D.B. Walden, and R.I. Greyson (Box 28)
  - Developmental Morphology of the Caryopsis in Maize, 1936; Randolph, L.F. (Box 28)
  - Retention of Euchlaena as a Genus Separate from Zea, [1972]; Randolph, L.F. (Box 28)
  - Transpositions, Mutable Genes, and the Dispersed Gene Family Dm225 in Drosophila melanogaster, 1980; Rasmuson, B., B.M. Westerberg, Å. Rasmuson, et al. (Box 28)
  - Different Rates of Crossing Over in Male and Female Gametes of Maize, 1941; Rhoades, Marcus M., (Marcus Morton), 1903-1991 (Box 28)
  - Elimination of Knobbed Chromosome Arms in Maize Induced by Supernumerary B Chromosomes, [1967]; Rhoades, Marcus M., Ellen Dempsey, and Achille Ghidoni (Box 28)
  - Genic Content and Structure of Abnormal Chromosome 10, 1980; Rhoades, Marcus M. and Ellen Dempsey (Box 28)
  - A Proposal for Creating an International Institute for Agricultural Research and Training to Serve the Lowland Tropical Regions of the Americas, Oct. 1966; Roberts, Lewis M. and Lowell S. Hardin (Box 28)
  - Biotechnology: Opportunities for Agricultural Research in Latin America, 11 Sep. 1984; Roca, W.M. (Box 28)
    See also Ser.III, Comments on Dr. Roca's Presentation
  - The Role of Cell Death in Morphogenesis of the Embryonic Limb, 1976; Rose, Mark (Box 28)
  - Prehistory of the West Indies, 1964; Rouse, Irving (Box 28)
  - The Molecular Weights of T2 Bacteriophage DNA and Its First and Second Breakage Products, Rubenstein, I., C.A. Thomas, Jr., and A.D. Hershey (Box 28)
  - Clave Para el Reconocimiento de Quiasmas en Metafase I, [196-]; Safont, Julio (Box 28)
  - General Report on the Activities Accomplished by Ingeniero Julio Safont at North Carolina State Under the Support of the Rockefeller Foundation, [1963]; Safont, Julio (Box 28)
  - Remark on the Symbols Utilized for the Description of the Individual Results in the Enclosed Lists, [196-]; Safont, Julio (Box 28)
  - Agrobacterium tumefaciens: What Segment of the Plasmid Is Responsible for the Induction of Crown Gall Tumors?, Schell, J., M. Van Montagu, A. De Picker, et al. (Box 28)
  - Structure and Evolution of Goat t -, Betac- and BetaA- Globin Genes: Three Developmentally Regulated Genes Contain Inserted Elements, 1981; Schon, Eric A., Michael L. Cleary, Joel R. Haynes, and Jerry B. Lingrel (Box 28)
  - Controlling Element Mutants and Chromosome Structure, [1972]; Schwartz, Drew (Box 28)
  - The Effect of Ac Dosage on the Production of Multiple Forms of Wx Protein by the wxm-9 Controlling Element Mutation in Maize, 1982; Schwartz, Drew and Craig S. Echt (Box 28)
  - Evidence for the Inclusion of Controlling Elements Within the Structural Gene at the Waxy Locus in Maize, 1981; Schwartz, Drew and Craig S. Echt (Box 28)
  - On the Tissue Specific Regulation of Gene Function: Pre-setting and Erasure, 1982; Schwartz, Drew (Box 28)
  - Concentric Rings in E. coli Colonies, 1990; Shapiro, James A. (Box 28)
  - Eukaryotic Mobile and Repeated Genetic Elements, 1981; Shapiro, James A. and Barbara Cordell (Box 28)
  - Genomic Reorganization in Cell Lineages, n.d.; Shapiro, James A. (Box 28)
  - The Initial Cell Divisions in the E. coli K-12 Colony, [1988]; Shapiro, James A. and Clara Hsu (Box 28)
  - Intercellular Communication and Genetic Change in Bacterial Populations, 1985; Shapiro, James A. (Box 28)
  - Mobile Genetic Elements and Cellular Differentiation, [1982]; Shapiro, James A. (Box 28)
  - Observations on the Formation of Clones Containing araB-lacZ Cistron Fusions, n.d.; Shapiro, James A. (Box 28)
  - Organization of Developing E. coli Colonies Viewed by Scanning Electron Microscopy, [1986]; Shapiro, James A. (Box 28)
  - Reflections on the Information Content of Chromosome Primary Structure and How it Changes, 1981; Shapiro, James A. (Box 28)
  - Sectoring in E. coli Colonies, n.d.; Shapiro, James A. (Box 29)
  - Sequential Events in Bacterial Colony Morphogenesis, [1990]; Shapiro, James A. and David Trubatch (Box 29)
  - Some Lessons of Phage Mu, [1985]; Shapiro, James A. (Box 29)
  - Unidentified, [198-]; Shapiro, James A. (Box 29)
  - Variation of Beta-Galactosidase Expression from Mudlac Elements During the Development of E. coli Colonies, [1987]; Shapiro, James A. and N. Patrick Higgins (Box 29)
  - The Isolation, Culture, and Regeneration of Plant Protoplasts, 1981; Shepherd, James F. (Box 29)
  - Cytogenetic Studies of Neurospora crassa, 1948; Singleton, Jesse Robertson (Box 29)
  - Episomic Suppression of Phenotype in Salmonella, 1964; Smith-Keary, P.F. and G.W.P. Dawson (Box 29)
  - The Gene and Cell Differentiation, [1959]; Sonneborn, T.M., (Tracy Morton), 1905-1981 (Box 29)
  - Cloning of a Ds1-Homologous Element at the A1 Locus, 1986; Sorrentino, Jennifer J. and Nancy S. Shepherd (Box 29)
  - Sequence Characteristics of the rDt Controlling-Element, 1986; Sorrentino, Jennifer J., C. O'Reilly, Zs. Schwartz-Sommer, H. Saedler, and N.S. Shepherd (Box 29)
  - Analysis of Messenger RNA in Drosophila by In Situ Hybridization: Comparison of Cytoplasmic mRNA from Control and Heat Shocked Culture Cells, 1975; Spradling, Allan, Sheldon Penman, and Mary Lou Pardue (Box 29)
  - Drosophila Salivary Glands Polytene Chromosomes Studied by In Situ Hybridization, 1977; Spradling, Allan, Mary Lou Pardue, J.J. Bonner, and J.A. Lengyel (Box 29)
  - mRNA in Heat Shocked Drosophila Cells, 1977; Spradling, Allan, Mary Lou Pardue, J.J. Bonner, and J.A. Lengyel (Box 29)
  - Review of Information on Virus Associated Genetic Effects, 1969; Sprague, G.F. (Box 29)
  - Virus as a Mutagenic Agent in Maize, 1963; Sprague, G.F. H.H. McKinney, and Lester Greeley (Box 29)
  - The Experimental Modification of Heredity in Crop Plants. I. Induced Chromosomal Irregularities, 1931; Stadler, L.J. (Box 29)
  - Recovery Following Genetic Deficiency in Maize, 1930; Stadler, L.J. (Box 29)
  - Barbara McClintock's Controlling Elements: Now at the DNA Level, 1984; Starlinger, Peter and Hans-Peter Döring (Box 29)
  - Controlling Element Ds at the Shrunken Locus in Zea mays, 1981; Starlinger, Peter, Hans-Peter Döring, Martin Geiser, Edward Weck, Ulrike Courage-Tebbe, and Edith Tillmann (Box 29)
  - A Reexamination of McClintock's Controlling Elements in Maize in View of Recent Advances in Molecular Biology, 1980; Starlinger, Peter (Box 29)
  - Transdetermination in Leg Imaginal Discs of Drosophila melanogaster und Drosophila nigromelanica, 1981; Steiner, Emil, Maja Koller-Wiesinger, and Rolf Nöthiger (Box 29)
  - Spectrophotometric Evidence for the Presence of a Leuco-Precursor of Both Anthoxanthin and Anthocyanin Pigments in Asiatic Cotton Flowers, [1948]; Stephens, S.G. (Box 29)
  - Transposable Elements in Drosophila melanogaster: Polymorphisms in the Chromosomal Locations of Elements of 412, Copia, and 297 Dispersed Repeated Gene Families, 1979; Strobel, Edward, Pamela Dunsmuir, and Gerald M. Rubin (Box 29)
  - Preferential Segregation in Triplo-IV Females of Drosophila melanogaster, 1936; Sturtevant, A.H. (Box 29)
  - An Extrachromosomal Form of the Mu Transposons of Maize, n.d.; Sundaresan, Venkatesan and Michael Freeling (Box 29)
  - Regulation of DNA Replication and Variegation-Type Position Effects, 1964; Taylor, J. Herbert (Box 29)
  - Systematic Variation and Evolution of Organelle DNAs in the Genus Zea: Teosinte, 1979; Timothy, David H., C.S. Levings III, D.R. Pring, M.F. Conde, and J.L. Kermicle (Box 29)
  - Isolation and Characterization of a 1.7 kb Transposable Element from a Mutator Line of Maize, 1986; Walbot, Virginia and Loverine P. Taylor (Box 29)
  - Molecular Analysis of the Linear 2.3 kb Plasmid of Maize Mitochondria: Apparent Capture of tRNA Genes from the Main Mitochondrial Genome, Walbot, Virginia, Patricia Leon, and Patricia Bedinger (Box 29)
  - Some Cytogenetic Aspects of Gene Control Mechanisms, 1973; Wallace, Bruce and Thomas L. Kass (Box 30)
  - A Comparison of X-Ray Induced Mutations and Mutations Occurring Spontaneously in Ring Chromosomes in Maize, 1942; Weaver, Edward A. (Box 30)
  - Analysis of Nondisjunction Induced by the r-X1 Deficiency During Microsporogenesis in Zea mays L, Weber, David F. and Zuo-Yu Zhao (Box 30)
  - Detection of the Time of Occurrence of Nondisjunction Induced by the r-X1 Deficiency in Zea mays L, Weber, David F., Kevin D. Simcox, and Jeffery D. Shadley (Box 30)
  - Effect of Monosomy and Nullisomy on Pollen Development in Monosomics of Zea mays L, Weber, David F. and Zuo-Yu Zhao (Box 30)
  - Identification of the Genomic Locations of Duplicate Nucleotide Sequences in Maize by Analysis of Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphisms, n.d.; Weber, David F., Tim Helentjaris, and Scott Wright (Box 30)
  - Male Gametopyte Development in Monosomics of Maize, n.d.; Weber, David F. and Zuo-Yu Zhao (Box 30)
  - Mapping RFLP Loci in Maize Using B-A Translocations, n.d.; Weber, David F. and Tim Helentjaris (Box 30)
  - Patterns of Mitochondrial DNA Variation in Indigenous Maize Races of Latin America, Weissinger, A.K., D.H. Timothy, C.S. Levings III, and Major M. Goodman (Box 30)
  - Alterations in Gene Expression Mediated by DNA Insertions in the Waxy Gene of Maize, 1988; Wessler, Susan R., George Baran, and Marguerite Varagona (Box 30)
  - Molecular Cloning and Structure Characterization of the R Locus of Maize, 1988; Wessler, Susan R., Stephen L. Dellaporta, Irwin Greenblatt, Jerry Kermicle, and James B. Hicks (Box 30)
  - Phenotypic Diversity Mediated by the Transposable Maize Controlling Elements Ac and Spm, 1988; Wessler, Susan R. (Box 30)
  - The Splicing of Maize Transposable Elements from Pre-mRNA, 1988; Wessler, Susan R. (Box 30)
  - Behavior of the Spindle Attachment in Unequal Bivalents at Meiosis, White, M.J.D. (Box 30)
  - Autoradiographische Untersuchungen zum Vermehrungsmuster der Zellen in Proliferierenden Rüsselprimordien von Drosophila melanogaster, 1968; Wildermuth, HansRudolf (Box 30)
  - Plant Germplasm Resources, [1976]; Wilkes, Garrison (Box 30)
  - Mutation-Proof and Mutation-Prone Modes of Survival in Derivatives of Escherichia coli B Differing in Sensitivity to Ultraviolet Light, 1967; Witkin, Evelyn M. (Box 30)
  - Partial Suppression of the LexA Phenotype by Mutations (rnm) Which Restore Ultraviolet Resistance But Not Ultraviolet Mutability to Escherichia coli B/r uvrA lexA, [1975]; Witkin, Evelyn M., Michael Volkert, and Donna L. George (Box 30)
  - The Role of DNA Repair and Recombination in Mutagenesis, 1968; Witkin, Evelyn M. (Box 30)
  - The Relationship Between Cytomixis, Chromosome Mutation and Karyotype Evolution in Lily, [1986]; Zheng, Guochang, Yang Quinglan, and Zheng Yongren (Box 30)
- Series V. Research notes and card files, 1930s-1990s; 55 linear feet
  Loose notes, notebooks, card files, and numerous photographs of maize. Because this series documents specific experiments with maize in great technical detail, the folders have been left in the original order in which they were boxed from McClintock's laboratory file cabinets at Cold Spring Harbor. The boxes have been labeled with the cabinet number and drawer number; for a map showing the location of these file cabinets in McClintock's laboratory, see the legal file. Most of the notes remain in folders labeled by McClintock; folders which were extremely acidic were replaced with acid-free folders, and McClintock's labels were copied onto the new folders. Loose notes remain in the boxes as found but were placed in unlabeled acid-free folders. All metal fasteners were removed and replaced with plastic clips when necessary. The notebooks are interspersed with the loose notes in the order in which McClintock arranged them. The card files (27.75 linear feet located at the end of Series V) are mainly culture cards for maize samples, which McClintock studied at Cold Spring Harbor. Many of the prints and slides are probably photographs of these same maize samples. The photographs were not removed to Series VI but left in context in Series V since many are interspersed with research notes.
  Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zea (maize) genetics
- Series VI. Photographs, 1928-1991; 1.5 linear feet
  Includes prints and negatives. Some of the prints are illustrations from articles about maize genetics, many from articles in Series IV, and some from McClintock's book, Chromosome Constitution of Races of Maize. Besides the folders filed under McClintock's name, there are other folders, which contain prints of her. These are filed as: "Blumenschein, Almiro; Kato Yamakake, Takeo Angel; and Barbara McClintock"; "Dunn, L.C. and Barbara McClintock"; "Hershey, Al and Barbara McClintock"; "Albert Lasker Clinical Medical Research Award"; "Marine Biological Laboratory"; "National Medal of Science"; "Nobel Prize #1"; "Possible Short-Term Evolutionary Consequences of Biotechnology"; "Rosenstiel Award"; "Stadler Symposium"; and "Yale University".
  - "Aug. 30, 1950." (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Diagram of chromosome breakage., 1950 August 30
  - Blumenschein, Almiro; Angel Kato Yamakake; and Barbara McClintock. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Almiro Blumenschein, Takeo Angel Kato Yamakake and Barbara McClintock gathered around table, 1966.
  - Cornell University, 1928. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - View of men with dogs, Cornell Department of Plant Breeding, 1928.
  - Cornell University, 1929 or 1930 (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Group portrait, Cornell University's Department of Plant Breeding.
  - Hershey, Al and Barbara McClintock (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Al Hershey and Barbara McClintock.
  - "Inactivation of the Maize Transposable Element Activator (Ac) is associated with its DNA Modification." (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Maize active/inactive photos., n. d.
  - McClintock, Barbara, ca. 1918. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - McClintock family at piano.
  - McClintock, Barbara, [192-?]. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Barbara McClintock, half length portrait, ca. 1925.
  - McClintock, Barbara, ca. 1960. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - McClintock, standing outside, half length portrait.
    - Barbara McClintock, standing outside with cigarette holder.
    - Barbara McClintock in cornfield, postcard.
  - McClintock, Barbara, 11 May, 1972. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Barbara McClintock seated at desk., 1972 May 11
  - McClintock, Barbara, 1980. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Barbara McClintock portrait, 1980.
  - McClintock, Barbara #2, 24 May 1982. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Barbara McClintock, in academic robe, walking in Yale procession., 1982 May 24
  - McClintock, Barbara, 7 Nov. 1983. (Box A – McClintock 1983)
    - Barbara McClintock, portrait., 1983 November 7
  - McClintock Family, 1954, 1958-1959, n.d. (Box McClintock 1984 – Shapiro #1)
    - Four McClintock children.
  - McClintock, Barbara #2 [198-?]. (Box McClintock 1984 – Shapiro #1)
    - Barbara McClintock wearing Groucho Marx glasses., ca. 1985
  - Nobel Prize #1, [8 Dec. 1983] (Box McClintock 1984 – Shapiro #1)
    - Barbara McClintock at Nobel lecture., 1983 December 8
  - Rosenstiel Award, 1978. (Box McClintock 1984 – Shapiro #1)
    - Barbara McClintock, at Rosenstiel Award ceremony, standing beside unidentified man., 1978
  - Stadler Symposium at University of Missouri, April, 1978 (Box Shapiro #2 – Y)
    - Barbara McClintock at Stadler Symposium at University of Missouri, April, 1978., 1978 April
- Series II, IV. Oversized (Oversize 1)
  - Series II. Subject files
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1959
    - American Philosophical Society, 1946
    - Botanical Society of America, 1957
    - Gembloux Agricultural College, 1985
    - Georgetown University, 1981
    - Harvard University, 1979
    - National Academy of Sciences, 1944
    - Rockefeller University, 1979
    - Rutgers University, 1984
    - Wolf Foundation, 1981
  - Series IV. Works by others
    - Remark on the Symbols Utilized for the Description of the Individual Results in the Enclosed Lists, [196-]; Safont, Julio